A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Director, Herbert Spencer Gasser, Correspondence, Series 2 FA143
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Director, Herbert Spencer Gasser, Correspondence, Series 2
1935-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA143
1.76 Cubic Feet 4 boxes
4 boxes.
Related Materials
Herbert Spencer Gasser was Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research 1935-1953. During his tenure he continued many of the administrative routines which had been established during the directorship of Simon Flexner. Thus, much administrative correspondence, in particular, matters dealing with personnel and administration of the physical plant are to be found in the papers of the Business Manager, Edric B. Smith, who served also, as Secretary of the Board of Trustees.
See FA137 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Subject Files, Series 3. See FA809 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Series 4.
Biographical/Historical note
Herbert Spencer Gasser, 1888-1963, physiologist, was Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1935-1953. His early work at the University of Wisconsin and at Washington University was done on circulation and respiration, including the mechanism through which the heart is accelerated in exercise and the rate of decreased oxidation in the respiratory center. Later at Washington University and at Cornell University Medical College his major interest was in the physiology of nerve, developing electrophysiological techniques through the development of vacuum tube amplification and the cathode ray oscillograph. In collaboration with Joseph Erlanger, also of Washington University, he developed an exhaustive determination of the constants of nerve fibers and the classification of nerve fibers in accordance with their properties. The two men shared the Nobel Prize in Medicine and Physiology in 1944 for this work.
Biographical Note
1888 Born July 5 Platteville, Wisconsin
1907 Graduate State Normal School of Wisconsin, Platteville
1910 A.B. University of Wisconsin
1911 A.M. University of Wisconsin
1911-1912 Assistant in physiology University Wisconsin
1912-1913 Instructor in physiology, University Wisconsin
1915 M.D. Johns Hopkins University Medical School
1915-1916 Instructor in pharmacology, University Wisconsin
1916-1918 Instructor in physiology, Washington University St. Louis
1918-1920 Associate in physiology, Washington University
1920-1921 Associate Professor in physiology, Washington University
1921-1931 Professor in pharmacology, Washington University
1923-1925 Study abroad: University College, London; National Institute of Medical Research, London; Sorbonne, Paris; University of Munich
1931-1935 Professor physiology, Cornell University Medical College New York, New York
1935-1953 Director, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York, New York
1953 June, retired as Director; returned to work in his laboratory; Member Emeritus RIMR
1963 Died May 11 New York Hospital, New York, N.Y. Cremated; ashes sent to sister. Interred family plot, Platteville, Wis.
Prizes
1944 Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine Shared with Dr. Joseph Erlanger
1954 Kober Medal, Association of American Physicians
Clubs Sigma Xi, Gamma Alpha, Alpha Omega Alpha, Century Club, Quadrangle Club
Honorary Degrees
1936 D. Sc. university of Pennsylvania
1940 D. Sc. University of Rochester
1940 LL. D. Washington University
1941 D. Sc. University of Wisconsin
1945 D. Sc. Columbia University
1947 LL. D. Johns Hopkins University
1947 D. Sc. Oxford University
1948 D. Sc. Harvard University
1949 Doctor Honoris Causa, Université Libre de Bruxelles
1949 Doctor of Medicine, Honorary. Université Catholique de Louvain
1953 Honorifique de docteur. Université de Paris
1959 D. Sc. The Rockefeller University
Served
1918 Pharmacologist, Chemical Warfare Service
1936 Johnson Foundation Lecturer, University of Pennsylvania
1937- Rockefeller Foundation Trustee
1937- Russell Sage Institute of Pathology. Board of Directors
1941- Princeton University. Dept. of Biology
1941-1944 National Defense Research Committee Division 9
1945 Research Board for National Security (Member)
1947 Massachusetts General Hospital, Scientific Advisory Committee
Member of American Societies, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Fellow, American Association for the Advancement of Science, Fellow, American Neurological Association (Associate Member), American Philosophical Society, American Physiological Society, American Society of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics, American Society of Electroencephalography (Honorary), Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease, Association of American Physicians, Harvey Society (Councilor, Vice President, President), History of Science Society, National Academy of Sciences, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine (Pres. 1937-1939), New York State Society for Medical Research (Active Member, 1952), Foreign Societies, Academie Royale de Médecine de Belgique, correspondence member, Accademia della Scienze dell'Istituto di Bologna, correspondence member, Asociación Médica Argentina, Honorary Member, Finnish Academy of Sciences, Honorary Foreign Member, Physiological Society (British) Honorary Member, Royal Society of Edinburgh, Honorary Member, Royal Society of London, Honorary Member, Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, Foreign Member, Sociedad Argentina de Biologia, Honorary Member, Société Philomathique de Paris, Corresponding Member
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Herbert Spencer Gasser collection was deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives by The University.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 302-2
Other Finding Aids
FA813 Rockefeller University records, Herbert Spenser Gasser, Subject Files, Series 4.
FA814 Rockefeller University records, Herbert Spenser Gasser, Biography, Series 6.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Physiology; Medical research; Medical sciences; Viruses -- Research; Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer); National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); Princeton University; Flexner, Simon; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Correspondence, 1935-1961; 2; 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Including incoming and outgoing letters. Number in parenthesis indicates number of items. A concise description is included where correspondence is voluminous or deals with a subject of particular interest or covers a number of years.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically including incoming and outgoing letters.
  Scope and Contents
  Of the correspondence in the Gasser papers, no clear distinction between administrative, professional and personal matters is apparent. They are in one alphabetical arrangement. A small amount of correspondence which is clearly personal, such as letters of appointment, receipt of honorary degrees and congratulatory letters on appointment as Director of the Institute and other honors (particularly Nobel Prize matters) were maintained in separate files and have been inventoried and listed with biographical and laboratory papers in the Biographical Material, Series 6 (FA814).
  - A (Box 1)
    - Academic Press, 1 item
    - Académie Royale de Médecine de Belgique. Lord Adrian (5) 3 holographs from Lord Adrian, 1 item
    - Albritton, Errett C. (Handbook of Biological Data-4)
    - Allen, Raymond A. Inquiry about staff appointment, 2 items
    - Amberson, William R., 1949-1958; 6 items
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1948; 1 item
    - American Cancer Society. Reference for M. Cattell, 2 items
    - American Journal of Physiology, 2 items
    - American Philosophical Society, 5 items
    - American Physiological Society, 3 items
    - Angevine, D. Murray. Refusal as representative to AAAS, 1954; 2 items
    - Animal Welfare Institute, 3 items
      Includes pamphlets.
    - Army Institute of Pathology. request of Raymond du Bois biography, 1949; 4 items
    - Arvanitaki-Chalazonitis, A., 2 items
    - Association of American Physicians. Award of Kober Medal Aström, Karl-Erik (1), 1954; 5 items
    - Auwarter, George. request for reprints, 1962; 3 items
    - Avery Memorial Gateway, 1 item
    - Azuma, R. 3 holographs, 1948-1958; 11 items
  - B (Box 1)
    - Bachmann, Warner E. decision to remain at University of Mich, 1947; 2 items
    - Barker, David. Request for recommendation for funds for research on mammalian proprioceptors, 1957-1958; 14 items
    - Barr, David, 2 items
    - Baud, C.-A, 1 item
    - Bauer, K. Fr. Medizinische Grundlegenforschung, 4 items
    - Beecher, Henry K. Definition of pain and publication, 1956-1960; 8 items
    - Beidler, Lloyd M., 1 item
    - Bell, George H., 1 item
    - Beritoff, J., 1 item
    - Blinks, L.R. Hurricane damage at Woods Hole, 1954; 3 items
    - Bliss, C.I., 3 items
    - Bloom, William, 5 items
    - Bluemel, Elinor. on Florence Sabin biography, 2 items
    - Botar, J., 2 items
    - Bouman, H.D. publication of Muscular Dystrophy Symposium, 1954; 8 items
    - Bovet, Daniel, 3 items
    - Brandly, C.A. request for R.E. Shope biography, 2 items
    - Brinley, F.J., 2 items
    - Bronk, John R. recommendation for Rhodes Scholar, 1951; 2 items
    - Buchthal, Fritz, 1 item
    - Busser, John H. Circuit changes on oscilloscope, 1 item
    - Bishop, George. Professional correspondence between colleagues with ties of friendship, 1935-1958; 51 items
    - Bronk, Detlev W., 1935-1959; 57 items
      Correspondence between friends who are also professional colleagues which includes plans for vacation trips as well as arrangements for lectureships or honors. Includes arrangements for Gasser/Erlanger Johnson Foundation lectures in 1936. Includes 1939 Bronk biographical sketch and bibliography (5 holographs) and 1950 photo at Welch Centennial dinner.
    - Bush, Vannevar. for OSRD dealing with Gasser appointment to advisory committee on administration of contracts with pharmaceutical firms, University labs and Department of Agriculture for synthesis of penicillin and possible conflict with position taken for royalty free patent rights, 1944-1946; 13 items
  - C (Box 1)
    - Cannon, P.J., 2 items
    - Carlson, A.J. antivivisectionist problems, 1944 1947; 6 items
    - Carpenter, F.J., 2 items
    - Carter, R.B. National Cyclopedia of Am. Biography, 3 items
    - Castro, Ferdinand de. in honor of Ramon y Cajal, 2 items
    - Cauna, N. with 3 enclosures, 5 items
    - Chase, Merrill. plus copies of papers by Elizabeth W. Kidwell, 1 item
    - Chatfield, Paul O., 4 items
    - Chen, K.K., 2 items
    - Chinard, G., 2 items
    - Clark, W. Mansfield. search for candidate for chairmanship of Johns Hopkins chemistry dept, 4 items
    - Clayson, B. International Who's Who, 3 items
    - Clegg, H.A. British Medical Journal 80th birthday article on Sir Henry Dale, 1955; 8 items
    - Clegg, L.L. Medical School reference for Charles Singleton, 2 items
    - Cohn, Alfred E., 4 items
    - Corner, G.W., 1 item
    - Cotzias, George C., 3 items
    - Creasy, William N., 3 items
    - Carty (John J.) Medal and Award for the Advancement of Science ca. 1 inch. Established in 1930 by AT&T administered by NAS, 1946-1952
      Includes copies of correspondence while Isaiah Bowman chairman. Gasser became chairman in 1948 until 1952. 1947 award to Ross G. Harrison; 1950 award to Irving Langmuir.
    - Conant, James B., 1941-1951; 14 items
      Includes pamphlet "Clear and Present Danger".
    - Dale, Henry, 1940-1959; 18 items
      Correspondence between friendly colleagues over 19 years. Includes penciled draft of HSG letter.
  - D (Box 1)
    - Dodds, Harold Willis. concerning James B. Stokes wish to be considered for an honorary degree, 1946; 2 items
    - Doyle, William L. with copy of Respiratory Project at The University of Chicago toxicity laboratory prepared by E.M.K. Geiling, 1 item
  - E (Box 1)
    - Easton, Dexter M., 1 item
    - Eggleton, M. Grace. on 75th birthday celebration of A.V. Hill, 1961; 3 items
    - Eisenhart, L.P. APS request for biographical memoir of Alan Gregg, 4 items
    - Eisenman, George, 2 items
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 7 items
      Includes copy for Joseph Erlanger article.
    - Engelgardt, V.A. in Russian, 1 item
    - Esmond, William G., 4 items
      Includes phase photo of myelinated nerve fiber.
    - Estable, Clemente, 2 items
    - Evans, Lovalt. University of London, 1 item
    - Eccles, J.C. Discussions of mutual interests in neurophysiology. Some holographs, 1935-1957; 32 items
    - Erlanger, Joseph (ca. 1 inch) Mentor and colleague at Washington University. Shared Nobel Prize with H.S. Gasser in 1944. Correspondence deals with collaboration on Johnson Foundation lectures; questions in neurophysiology. Correspondence is both friendly and professional. Many holograph letters, 1935-1957
  - F (Box 1)
    - Fahrney, D.S. request for D.W. Bronk career history, 3 items (Box 1)
    - Farr, Lee E. Requesting evaluation of Irving L. Schwartz, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Fawcett, Don W., 1 item (Box 1)
    - Feindel, William, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Felberg, W., 4 items (Box 1)
    - Fenton, Charles. request for recollections of Stephen Vincent Benet, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Ferguson, Malcolm. inquiry as to staff opening, 1 item (Box 1)
    - Fernandez-Moran, H. Symposium at Venezuelan Institute for Neurology in Caracas, 1957 March 15-22; 24 items (Box 1)
    - Fessard, A. Symposium in Paris 1955 July 19-23 not attended, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Filho, J.S.R., 2 items (Box 1)
    - Fisher, Knight and Co. On reprints of Sir Henry Dale article, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Flexner, Abraham, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Flexner, Morris, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Folkers, Karl. 1954 on Dr. Lorente de No, 1 item (Box 1)
    - Fosdick, Mrs. Paulding. on son's myesthenia gravis, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Fosdick, Raymond B. "Thank you" for book on Rockefeller Foundation, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Fowler, Virginia M. recommendation letter, 1 item (Box 1)
    - Fred, E.B. re names for deanship at Wisconsin Med. Sch, 3 items (Box 1)
    - Funaoka, Seigo, 1 item (Box 1)
    - Furth, J. for help in building a centrifuge, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Fenn, Wallace. Professional colleague at the University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry. A member of original "Axonology group", 1936-1956; 46 items (Box 1)
    - Fulton, John F., 1936-1960; circa 1 inch (Box 2)
      Professional correspondence including many, items relating to publication of Journal of Neurophysiology. 1939 correspondence in relation to displaced scientists such as O. Loewi; correspondence about publications of symposia and other volumes. Member of original "Axonology group".
  - G (Box 2)
    - Gallego, Antoine. Permission to publish inaugural address of Apr. 3, 1956, 1956 April 3; 6 items
    - Gallego, Jose Luis, 2 items
    - Gelfan, Samuel, 1 item
    - Gerard, Ralph W. in "Axonology group". President of American Physiological Society, 1935-1953; 35 items
    - Gibbs, Frederic A.A Brain Research Foundation, 5 items
    - Gilson, A.S. 50th anniversary Washington University School of Medicine, 2 items
    - Graham, Evarts, 1 item
    - Graham, Evarts, Jr., 2 items
    - Granit, Ragnar, 1943-1951; 25 items
      Includes typed copy of English address of Nobel Prize ceremony.
    - Grants Study Photograph of participants at Conference with names, 1939 November 10
    - Greene, Jerome Covering letter of Henry James (author) recollection of RIMR visit [see RG 417]
    - Grenell, Robert G. regarding a Symposium on Progress in Neurobiology, 1960; 3 items
    - Griffin, D.R., 1 item
    - Graham, Helen Treadway is concerned with a review article for Physiological Reviews, 1935-1952 1936-1939; 92 items
    - Gregg, Alan, suggesting a medical council to promote greater responsibility in medical practice. Comments by T.M. Rivers and HSG. Some addresses and articles used by HSG in preparation of APS Biographical Memoir, 1957; 15 items
  - H (Box 2)
    - Habel, Robert E., 6 items
    - Hanscom, Dean. Bell Laboratories, 1 item
    - Harington, Sir Charles, 2 items
    - Harrison, Ross C., 4 items
    - Harvey, A. McGehee, 1 item
    - Hartman, Elizabeth C. Recommendation for Harry Grundfest, 2 items
    - Hastings, Baird. enclosing directions for a solution, 1 item
    - Henry, Barklie, 3 items
    - Herlitzka, -., 1 item
    - Hillemann, Howard H., 2 items
    - Hodge, Harold C., 2 items
    - Hodges, Paul C. On Erlanger article for Ency. Brit., 2 items
    - Houssay, B. on visit of Dr. Braun-Menendez, 2 items
    - Howell, William H. On length of article for JEM, 3 items
    - Hughes, Jack. invitation to lecture and dinner for F.O. Schmitt, 2 items
    - Hunt, Carlton C. (8 plus 17p. enclosure)
    - Hill, A.V., 1936-1951; 28 items
    - Hinsey, Joseph C., 1935-1959; 69 items
    - Hodgkin, Alan, 1937-1960; 24 items
  - I (Box 2)
    - Iggo, A., 2 items
    - Isbell, Harris, 1 item
    - International Physiological Congress, 1937-1950; 3 folders
      This correspondence is divided by subject into three folders and each is arranged in chronological order.
      - Correspondence, 1937-circa 1939; 1 inch
        Biographical/Historical note
        Gasser served on a Standing Committee of the Federation on International Congresses with Drs. Walter B. Cannon and Donald Van Slyke with responsibility to pass on Federation membership of papers submitted by Local Committees for presentation at the XVIth International Physiological Congress in Zürich, August 14-18, 1938. The Standing Committee also had responsibility in the award of Congress Fellowships. The Federation Secretary served as ex officio on this Committee.
        The correspondence is primarily between H.S. Gasser and W.B. Cannon but includes some letter from A.C. Ivy, secretary of the American Physiological Society and D.R. Hooker, Federation Secretary and W.R. Hess of the Zürich Committee. Some correspondence covering papers submitted from: Bernard S. Oppenheimer, G. Philip Grabfield, Selig Hecht, E. Rothlin, H.K. Hartline, D.W. Bronk, Kenneth Cole, Joseph S. Fruton. Also includes handwritten note from A.V. Hill (Aug. 14, 1938) Report on Congress: Science, 88 (1938) Report to D.R. Hooker of Standing Committee by W. Cannon for meeting April 1939.
      - History of International Physiological Congress, 1940-1947
        Folder 10 consists of this copy and historical notes and summaries made by Dr. Gasser. It also includes a photograph of the 7th Congress held in Heidelberg, it bears a note by HSG "Copied from photograph in possession of Johannsson, 1938" Some identification has been supplied by H.S. Gasser and further information added from Annals of Science v. 3 July 1938 pp. 241-236. "History of the International Congresses of Physiologists" by K.J. Franklin.
        Correspondents include: A.V. Hill, E.D. Adrian, W.R. Hess, G. Liljestrand, Wallace Fenn, A.J. Carlson and deals with XVIIth International Congress in Oxford, Eng. 22-25 July 1947 dealing with question of not sending invitations to Germans.
        Custodial History note
        In the spring of 1941, Prof. A.V. Hill turned over the records of the Congress to H.S. Gasser for safekeeping during the bombing of London. Dr. Gasser thus became the custodian of the secretaryship. In 1946, after World War II, all records were sent to Prof. G. Liljestrand. A typescript copy of the Minute Book of the Permanent International Committee was made for Dr. Gasser's file and as a precaution against loss.
    - International Union of Physiology, 1948-1950
      Consists of the correspondence between H.C. Bazett, H.S. Gasser and A.C. Ivy serving as a Committee to consider the formation Of an International Union of Physiology. Consists of many suggestions and ideas from various members, penciled notes by H.S. Gasser with suggested statutes for the formation of such a union. Also included is a typescript copy of an abstract of paper "Unmedullated Fibers Originating in Dorsal Root Ganglia" submitted by H.S.G. for presentation at XVIII Congress in Copenhagen. The original statutes for the Union of Physiology were not approved, but in February of 1950 a revised version was presented for consideration of The International Council of Scientific Unions, with the proposal that the present International Committee function until the transition to Union is complete. A letter from Ralph W. Gerard of 1950 Sept. 8 reports that at the XVIIIth International Physiological Congress in Copenhagen the mission of reporting on an International Union of Physiology was accomplished and the Committee discharged.
  - J (Box 3)
    - Jakus, Marie A. on retina nerve fibers, 2 items
    - Jasper, Herbert H., 1 item
    - Johansen, John C. On painting of portrait, 2 items
    - Johnson, J.B. On 1922 Western Electric tube, 1 item
    - Johnson & Higgins. Insurance claim, 1 item
    - Journal of Biophysical and Biochemical Cytology. Comments on Pease, Pallie manuscript, 1 item
    - Journal of General Physiology, 3 items
    - Jung, R. Contribution to Paul Hoffmann Festschrift, 4 items
  - K (Box 3)
    - Karaagac, Ihsan, 2 items
    - Kidd, John G. 1944 acceptance of resignation from RI 1953 letter of recommendation of George Murphy, 4 items
    - Kidwell, Elizabeth Willcox, 3 items
    - Kirk, Grayson, 4 items
    - Knipping, W., 1 item
    - Knight, Clifford, 2 items
    - Koll, W., 3 items
    - Krivoy, W.A., 2 items
    - Kubie, Lawrence S. (3 and enclosures)
    - Kuffler, Stephen, 11 items
      Includes 16 page undated review study of Kuffler's publication with 2 pages of penciled notes and a request from Otto Krager, Harvard Medical School for an evaluation.
  - L (Box 3)
    - Lain Entralgo, P. in reference to article for publication at Centenario de Santiago Ramon y Cajal, 9 items
    - LaPorte, Yves, 2 items
    - Laudati, Anthony, 2 items
    - Lehmann, H.J., 6 items
    - Loeb, Robert F., 5 items
      Includes typed carbon copy excerpt from 1952 annual report to Columbia U. Med. Sch. Dean.
    - Liljestrand, G., 1945-1953; 26 items
      Includes Nobel Prize recommendations for Ragnar Granit and H. Keffer Hartline (became recipients in 1967).
    - Longcope, Warfield T., 1946-1953; 32 items
      Includes draft with corrections of Memorial Minute at death of James B. Murphy (1950) and copies of Oct. 1952 Minute presented at Longcope retirement from Board. Most letters from Longcope are handwritten.
    - Lorente de No, R. Handwritten letters sent during year spent abroad for health reasons, 1950-1951; 12 items
      Included is a short sketch of his work.
  - M (Box 3)
    - McCarthy, F.J., 2 items
    - MacInnes, D. Congratulations on 70th birthday, 2 items
    - MacIntyre, Archie, 2 items
    - Mackay, Ian F.S. request, for photograph, 2 items
    - Marine Biological Laboratory, 1 item
    - Marshall, Wade H., 2 items
    - Merkulov, W.L., 3 items
    - Mettler, Cecilia, 2 items
    - Michaelis, L., 2 items
      Includes copy of Memorial Minute.
    - Miller, Alice. Thank you for flowers from Childrens' Gardens, 2 items
    - Miller, Frederick, 5 items
    - Mirsky, A.E. Contributions to JGP, 2 items
    - Moe, Henry Allen. Recommendation to Guggenheim Found, on grant request by Stephen W. Kuffler, 2 items
    - Monnier, Ali and Andre. Some correspondence on University of Paris honorary degree, 7 items